<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
    <p n="one">I received particular joy at seeing, within the smell of the land, an Old Yorkshire
        man of foreseer who had left his son a merchant in <location place="city">New
            York</location>, to breath his last in his native land; far from the continued storms we
        met &amp; feeble situation he was in from sea sickness I had been apprehensive we should
        have lost him on the passage.</p>

    <p n="two">Coasting the Southwest shore of <location place="country">Ireland</location> on that
        18th in the evening we made Cork, where we were (sp. where) becalmed – we met there a ship
        we had seen two days before at a distance, she was an armed vessel of Liverpool, that had
        been at Barbados, and was now returning, she had on board the Governor, and suite of a Dutch
        settlement in the <location place="mountains">West Indies,</location> lately taken by the
        British troops – There is not much appearance of verdure yet on shore – or it might in some
        respect afford a beautiful prospect – <rewrote>but they have a disagreeable way of
            decorating their coasts with <unsure>gibbets (sp. jibbets)</unsure> here and
            there</rewrote>
        <!-- the line was scribbbled out and rewrote again --> – Is it not surprising, that a people
        so enlightened, so humane and so polite should have it so arranged, that the first object
        striking the view of the strangers, who approach their shore
        <!-- was crossed out and rewrote for {shore} --> should be an emblem of the severity of
        their laws and depravity of some of their people. Telegraphs were also to be seen on every
            <above>eminence</above>
        <!-- the word was wrote above the crossed out --> – this is a late invention to communicate
        intelligence of the approach of an enemy or to give orders to the ships of the Navy – they
        are on a line of repeated from one <page jumps="25">(jumps to next page; p.25)</page> to the
        other without being understood by any but those from whom the orders issue and the
        commanders of Posts. We there learnt, by the boats which came from the shore, that all was
        as yet tranquil, that they had only heard of the threats of Bonaparte which it was not
        likely, he would be able to put in execu-tion.</p>

    <p n="three">After night a fair wind springing up, we made sail, and next morning,
            <added>we</added>
        <!-- added to it after the next word was written --> were a breast of Wicklow Moun-tains,
        the land is high and elevated, but we were at too great a distance to distinctly view it –
        On the <date>21st</date> we sailed along the Welsh Coast and <unsure>(does not look like
            passed) passed</unsure> Holy head – here is elevated land &amp; lofty mountains, whose
        tops are covered with snow, which although they do not prepossess <above>you</above>
        <!-- added to it after the next word was written --> with an idea of the fertility of the
        country, yet the <above>natural</above>
        <!-- added to it after the next word was written --> Majestic grandeur of the
            <crossed-out>/</crossed-out> asylum of the descendants of ancient <above>Britons</above>
        <!-- added to it after the next word was written --> strikes the mind with veneration at the
        magnanimity and unfortunate valor of their ancestors who preferred breathing the air of
        freedom on <location place="mountains">Rocky Mountains</location>, to remaining in
        subjection on their native fertile plains, and calls a sigh for their hero the gallant
        Caractacus.</p>

    <p n="four">In the evening a Pilot comes on board and next day we arrive safe in dock here, the
        pleasure we felt on the occasion can not well be imagined by any but those, who have made a
        long sea voyage. Altho’ this was Sunday and business lulled at rest, yet sufficient was to
        be seen to give a stranger some conception of the magnitude of the trade carried on at this
        place – the many store houses, the multitude of ships, the inland canals and docks all
        denote wealth &amp; exertion, these last are of two kind wet and dry, the latter are to
        receive vessels to be repaired; the former are for <page jumps="26">(next page, p.26)</page>
        ships to unload and load in; they are made by digging spaces to <above>such</above>
        <!-- added to it after the next word was written --> a level <crossed-out>/</crossed-out> as
        to be of sufficient depth for the vessels that are to <crossed-out>/</crossed-out>
        <!-- was written then crossed out then he wrote enter close to the crossed out one--> enter
        the gates of these docks at which the vessels, and flow of the tide are received, are shut
        in the ebb tide by which <above>means</above>
        <!-- added to it after the next word was written --> the water is retained that keeps the
        ships afloat – were it not for these constructions the lading and unlading would be
        performed with great inconvenience at this port which is not naturally well calculated, the
        River being amazing shallow at low water, and its entry rendered difficult from a number of
        sand banks.</p>

    <p n="five">But the approximate situation of this place to <above>several</above>
        <!-- added to it after some was crossed out and the next word was written -->
        <crossed-out>/</crossed-out> manufacturing town <crossed-out>/</crossed-out> renders it the
        great emporium of commerce to the West – It is here that are deposited the stuffs of
        Manchester, the cutlery of <location place="city">Birmingham</location> and the woolen
        cloths of <location place="city">Yorkshire</location>, as are also the produce of the west
        for which they are bartered – it is considered next to <location place="city"
            >London</location> for importance in trade: that of <location place="country"
            >Africa</location> however is a branch <crossed-out>/</crossed-out> that is carried on
        here to some extent <crossed-out>/</crossed-out> and is not <crossed-out>/</crossed-out>
        honorable to the human spe-cies; for it is a barter of their fellow creatures – you must not
        by this imagine, that the slaves are brought here, no, for none would be slaves after they
        had breathed the British air – they are bought in <location place="country"
            >Africa</location> for coarse clothes, arms spirits &amp; taken to the <location
            place="mountains">West Indies</location> and sold for the produce of these Islands,
        which is brought to this place &amp; from it taken to different parts of the country. </p>

</letter>
